# LUIS EDUARDO CASTELLANOS

le.castellanos10@uniandes.edu.co, Tel:+57 3502938469 **Economist** 

## **PROFILE**

My work and academic experience have allowed me to develop research, critical thinking, and leadership skills, supported by a deep commitment to quality and precision in data analysis and processing. I am recognized for the thoroughness of my work, my passion for teaching, and my desire to make a significant difference by positively impacting people's well-being.

## **EDUCATION**

Master in economics

GPA: 4.8/5

January 2023 - Present

Universidad de los Andes

**BA** in Economics

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Academic Exchange in Economics

GPA: 4.7/5 (Honors Degree)

Summer 2020

April 2022

Master's courses

Justus Liebig University Giessen, Germany

## RECENT EXPERIENCE

# Short Term Temporary (STT) - World Bank

March 2023 - Present

Poverty and Equity Practice Group

- · Supported the construction of the semiannual report on poverty and inequality in Latin America and the Caribbean, focusing on the outcomes for Brazil and Mexico.
- · Built statistics on informality and its characteristics in Latin American countries, including Colombia, Mexico, Brazil, and Uruguay.
- · Replicated microsimulations to project poverty and various labor market outcomes.
- · Conducted a literature review on climate change and natural disasters for East Asia and the Pacific for the Social Protection & Labor EAP unit.

## Research assistant - Yale University

October 2023 - January 2024

Dr. Carlos Felipe Balcazar

- Successfully executed data management and harmonization on multiple datasets featuring detailed administrative data related to collective action in the U.S. during the COVID-19 crisis, utilizing OCR technology and data-cleaning methods in R, STATA, and Python.
- Conducted literature reviews and achieved replication of key prior studies.

# Research assistant and co-author - Banco de la República

April 2022 - Abril 2023

Department of Communication and Economic Education

- · Developed comprehensive historical databases, successfully harmonizing macroeconomic data on key variables from 1923 to 2023. Utilized this data, combined with findings from systematic literature reviews, to critically analyze the historical impact of the Colombian Central Bank on the nation's economy.
- Executed advanced time-series econometric analyses to explore the long-term relationship between the surplus of means of payments and inflation in Colombia.

# Consultant - World Bank

March 2022 - July 2022

· Conducted meticulous, systematic searches in specialized databases, leading to a comprehensive literature review focused on practical and theoretical interventions for tackling social issues related to informality in developing countries.

# Research assistant - Berkeley University

March 2022 - December 2022

Dr. Yipei Zhang

· Processed microdata from Colombia's largest manufacturing survey to perform causal inference analysis, investigating the impact of tariff reforms on the Colombian enterprise ecosystem. This analysis was further enriched by conducting an extensive literature review on the commercial history of Colombia.

# Contractor - Ministry of Finance of Colombia

January 2022 - April 2022

Risk Subdirectorate

· Implemented models to analyze the optimal issuance of sovereign bonds intended to finance health expenses in territorial entities. I supported the monthly preparation of the National Government Debt Profile.

#### PUBLICATIONS AND WORKING PAPERS

## **Book chapters**

- · Castellanos, L. E. (2023). Opacity and Financial Secrecy: Understanding their Impacts on Fiscal and Social Stability in Colombia. In Pabón C. and Silva C. (Eds.), Challenges of Global Taxation: Towards an Inclusive, Sustainable and Equitable Global Taxation for Latin America and the Caribbean. Fedesarrollo. [In spanish]
- · Castellanos, L. E. (2023). Econometric Analysis of the Relationship between Price Levels and Excess Payment Methods, 1923-2022. Villar L., and Esguerra M. P. (Eds.), Essays on Economic History. A Hundred Years of the Bank of the Republic. Banco de la República.[In Spanish]

#### Published articles

· Castellanos, L. E. (2021). Diversifying the Economics Profession: The Long Road to Overcoming Discrimination and Sub-representation of Hispanics and African Americans. An Analysis of the United States between 1995-2019. Cuadernos de Economía, 40(84), 875–897. [In English]

## Working and discussion papers

- · Rodríguez-Pinilla, D. A., Castellanos-Rodríguez, L. E., López-Rodríguez, A., & Esguerra Umaña, M. P. (2024). Financial literacy and Financial Wellbeing: evidence from Colombia in a high inflation environment. Banco de la República. [In Spanish]
- · Ghorpade, Y.; Franco Restrepo, C.; Castellanos, Luis Eduardo. (2024) Social Protection and Labor Market Policies for the Informally Employed: A Review of Evidence from Low- and Middle-Income Countries. Social Protection and Jobs Discussion Paper; No. 2403. World Bank Group. [English]
- · Castellanos, L. E., Diaz, J. D., Dueñas, C. C., and León, A. F. (2021). Fisher Effect and Error Correction Model in Colombia, 1991-2020. Econografos, 165. [In Spanish].

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# Universidad de los Andes

 $\cdot$  Assistant teacher - History of economic thoughts.

Spring 2024

· Tutor - History of economic thoughts.

Spring 2023 & Fall 2023

## Universidad Nacional de Colombia

· Econometrics I.

Spring 2021 & Fall 2021

Static and dynamic modeling.
Static modeling.
Spring 2019

Macroeconomics II.
Economics fundamentals.
Fall 2018

# CONGRESSES AND PANELS

Rethinking the Global Tribulation (May 2 and 3, 2023). Organized by Fedesarrollo, DIAN, and the Ministry of Finance and Public Credit. Document presentation *Opacity and financial secrecy:* understanding their impacts on fiscal and social stability in Colombia. [In Spanish]

## **SKILLS**

Academic writing
R and RStudio

Excel
Eviews
Stata
Python
English
C1
German

## **DISTINCTIONS**

Honors Degree Francisco Pizano de Brigard Scholarship Universidad Nacional de Colombia Universidad de los Andes